John Francis Holme collection, 1886-1938 (bulk 1889-1903)
University of Arizona Libraries, Special Collections
John Francis Holme Collection, 1886-1938 (bulk 1889-1903)
MS 001
Holme, John Francis, 1868-1904
This collection includes over 750 of Holme's original drawings and etchings, 142 reproductions, 134 original drawings by students and associates, and all nine Bandar Log Press books; as well as correspondence, photographs, news clippings, and articles relating to the School of Illustration and the Bandar Log Press. In addition to Holme, authors of the Bandar Log Press books are Charles Dryden, William Robinson, Kirke La Shelle, and George Ade. Holme's drawings are illustrations for news stories, including coverage of the 1897 Luetgert trial and the 1893 World Columbian Exposition; drawings of people, theatrical performances, "life and times" scenes of the 1890s; political events and politicians, including coverage of the 1896 Democratic presidential convention, and political cartoons.
7 linear feet
University of Arizona Libraries, Special Collections University of Arizona PO Box 210055 Tucson, AZ 85721-0055 Phone: 520-621-6423 Fax: 520-621-9733 URL: http://speccoll.library.arizona.edu/
Restrictions
None.
Biographical Note
John Francis (Frank) Holme was a newspaper artist, chiefly in Chicago; he was the founder of the School of Illustration, Chicago and also founded the Bandar Log Press, 1895-1904, located successively in Chicago, Asheville, N.C., and Phoenix, Ariz.
Organization
This collection is organized into six series:
Series I: Personal Material, 1886-1986
Series II: Original Drawings, Prints and Paintings, 1897, No Date
Series III: Clippings and Art Reproductions, 1886-1986
Series IV: School of Illustration (Chicago) Staff and Student Art, 1898-1903
Series V: Biographical Material, 1898-1945?
Series VI: Bandar Log Press Books, 1895-1903
Scope and Content Note
This collection includes over 750 of Holme's original drawings and etchings, 142 reproductions, 134 original drawings by students and associates, and all nine Bandar Log Press books; as well as correspondence, photographs, news clippings, and articles relating to the School of Illustration and the Bandar Log Press. In addition to Holme, authors of the Bandar Log Press books are Charles Dryden, William Robinson, Kirke La Shelle, and George Ade. Holme's drawings are illustrations for news stories, including coverage of the 1897 Luetgert trial and the 1893 World Columbian Exposition; drawings of people, theatrical performances, "life and times" scenes of the 1890s; political events and politicians, including coverage of the 1896 Democratic presidential convention, and political cartoons.
Student and staff work from the School of Illustration includes one or two drawings each from various artists such as W.W. Denslow, John T. McCutcheon, Cyrus Leroy Baldridge, Wilfred B. Shaw, and Joseph C. Leydendecker. Photographs are of Holme, his family, and friends. News clippings and articles are either examples of Holme's work or about him. Also included are two signed Maxfield Parrish illustrations, one signed Bertha Jacques etching, and one W. Nicholson print of Queen Victoria.
Holme, John Francis, 1868-1904 -- Archives; McCutcheon, John T. (John Tinney), 1870-1949; Denslow, W.W. (William Wallace), 1856-1916; Baldridge, Cyrus Leroy, 1889; Shaw, Wilfred B.; Leydendecker, Joseph C.; Luetgert, Adolph Louis; Bandar Log Press; School of Illustration (Chicago, Ill.); Small press books -- Specimens; Small presses -- United States; Drawing -- Study and teaching -- United States; Editorial cartoons -- United States -- Specimens; Illustrators -- United States -- History; Drawing, American -- Specimens; Etching, American -- Specimens; Newspaper court reporting -- United States -- History -- 19th century; Newspapers -- Illustrations -- Specimens; Chicago (Ill.) -- Social life and customs -- Pictorial works; United States -- History -- 1865-1921 -- Caricatures and cartoons; Correspondence; Drawings; Illustrations; Etchings
Separated Material
Posters and publications received with the collection were removed and cataloged separately.
Container List
- Series I: Personal Material, 1886-1986
  - Photographs, Correspondence, Miscellaneous Material, 1891-1941
    - Frank Holme: miscellaneous material. (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Frank Holme: letters to LeRoy Baldridge. 1901-1903 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Frank Holme: photographs and sketches of. (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Frank Holme: photographs of friends and family. (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Frank Holme: photographs and sketches of friends and associates. (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - School of Illustration, Chicago: miscellaneous material. (Box 1, Folder 6)
      Includes advertisements, articles and photographs of staff.
    - Bandar Log Press: miscellaneous material. (Box 1, Folder 7)
      Includes list of stockholders, a prospectus, check-list and drawings by E. Powers, etc.
    - Miscellaneous correspondence. 1891-1931 (Box 1, Folder 8)
      Mrs. Ray Brown to Frank Holme, (one letter, no date).
      Frank Holme to his niece, Agnes Taylor, (nine letters, 1897-1902).
      Kirke LaShelle to Ray Brown and W. W. Denslow, ( two letters, December 21, 1891 and May 11, 1903).
      Mrs. Frank Holme to Wilfred Shaw, (three letters, 1906, 1931).
    - Holme items at the Huntington Library. (Box 1, Folder 9)
      List, photocopies of five letters from Kirke LaShelle (1902-1903) and Patricia Paylore's notes on Holme material (January 1961).
    - Holme items at West Virginia University. (Box 1, Folder 10-11)
      List, photocopies of drawings, clippings, and correspondence of Vause Marshall with Mrs. Frank Holme (1905, 1938-1940) and various others (1938-1941). Also an article about Frank Holme by Marshall.
    - Holme items at Southern Methodist University (DeGolyer Collection). (Box 1, Folder 12)
      List, with photocopies of four letters from Frank Holme to C. F. Witmarsh (1903) and one letter from Charles Sloan to Miss McMurrary (no date).
    - Three glass negatives of Holme's drawings. (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Miscellaneous art items. (Box 1, Folder 14)
      Two signed Maxfield Parrish illustrations.
      Signed Bertha Jacques etching.
      W. Nicholson print of Queen Victoria.
  - Correspondence, Articles, Etc. About Frank Holme, 1904-1986
    - Correspondence: Charles Sloan and University of Arizona Library. 1933-1939 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence: Edwin B. Hill and University of Arizona Library. 1935-1947 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Correspondence: Edwin B. Hill and various, (also some notes on Holme). 1929-1947 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Correspondence: University of Arizona Library and various. 1934-1986 (Box 2, Folder 4)
      Includes LeRoy Baldridge, Kirke LaShelle, Wilfred Shaw and Holme relatives.
    - Articles from The Inland Printer. 1904? (Box 2, Folder 5)
      "All About the Bandar Log Press." (original and photocopy).
      "Frank Holme, Artist."
      "The Man at the Window," by Thomas Wood Stevens (review of The Poker Rubaiyat).
      "The Bandar Log Press."
      "The Palette and Chisel Club."
    - Rudolph H. Gjelsness: drafts of articles and talks, notes, correspondence, etc. (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - "Radio Talk," by Fredrick Cromwell. Arizona Network. November 13, 1941 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Articles published in Arizona Highways. 1943 & 1968 (Box 2, Folder 8)
      "The Bandar Log Press," by Frederick Cromwell, March 1943.
      "All About the Bandar Log Press," by Tim Kelly, January 1968, accompanied by color reproductions of The Poker Rubaiyat used in the article.
    - Sketch book. (Box 3)
      Drawings and sketches, chiefly pencil. Most are probably by Holme, but some are signed by W. W. Denslow and others. A number are sketches of Holme. Includes holograph notes.
- Series II: Original Drawings, Prints and Paintings, 1897, No Date
  - Original drawings for certain of George Ade's works, (94 items). (Box 4)
  - Original drawings, (80 items). (Box 5)
    Color work (16)
    Cartoon styles (32)
    Children (6)
    Singers and dancers (8)
    Miscellaneous (18)
  - Original drawings, (134 items). (Box 6)
    Courtroom scenes (12)
    "Life and Times" groups (25)
    Identified people (7)
    People (77)
    Theater interiors, etc. (13)
  - Original drawings, (189 items). (Box 7)
    Theatrical performances: Merchant in Venice (14 items)
    Theatrical performances: Rip Van Winkle? (20 items)
    Theatrical performances: Turkish setting (49 items)
    Theatrical performances: miscellaneous (25 items)
    Theatrical performances: unidentified (72)
    Actors and actresses: three identified, three W. Hampden? (6 items)
    Unidentified actor as King Lear? (3 items)
  - Etchings and lithographs, (64 items). (Box 8)
  - Original illustrations for Luetgert Trial, Chicago (14 originals, 9 reproductions). 1897 (Box 9)
  - Original drawings, (80 items). (Box 10)
    Water colors (14 items)
    People (some identified) (31 items)
    Local events, "Life and Times" (18 items)
    Courtroom scenes (6 items)
    Army life (5 items)
    Miscellaneous (6 items)
  - Original drawings, (96 items) (Box 11)
    Political cartoons (25 items)
    Miscellaneous cartoons (10 items)
    Portraits; possibly of Holme's wife and mother (6 items)
    Political events and personalities including the Democratic Convention, Indianapolis, 1896 (26 items)
    Local scenes, "Life and Times" (15 items)
    Nudes (2 items)
    Theatrical performances (2 items)
    Sculpture class (2 items)
    Magazine sketch
    People, including signed portrait of actress Georgia Cayvan and singer-comedian Digby Bell (7 items)
  - Oil paintings, (2 items). (Box 12)
- Series III: Clippings and Art Reproductions, 1886-1986
  - Newspaper columns from the Chicago Daily News illustrated by Frank Holme. (Box 13)
    Some columns written by Holme. Notes supplied by Wilfred B. Shaw, donor and former student at the School of Illustration in Chicago.
  - Miscellaneous newspaper clippings relating to Frank Holme. 1886-1938 (Box 14)
    Extract from the Wheeling Daily Register showing a political cartoon by Holme, October 25, 1886 (photocopy)
    Extracts from the Pittsburgh Press with illustrations by Holme of the Johnstown flood, June 6, 7, 9, 1889 (photocopy)
    "Chicago Art Institute to Establish Etching Press," Chicago, ca. 1890
    " Poker Rubaiyat by Kirke LaShelle," New York Herald, April 26, 1903
    " Poker Rubaiyat, first book of Bandar Log Press," New York World, April 26, 1903
    "Fame Carved with a Jackknife," by Tom Kelland, Arizona Republic, May 15, 1938
  - Reproductions of drawings, lithographs, newspaper illustrations (142 items). (Box 15)
    Political scenes and cartoons (7 items)
    Miscellaneous cartoons (5 items)
    People (some identified) (17 items)
    Portraits of women (19 items)
    Local events, "Life and Times" (82 items)
    Miscellaneous (12 items).
- Series IV: School of Illustration (Chicago) Staff and Student Art, 1898-1903
  A great many of the artists represented could not be fully identified, either from the signatures on their drawings or in bibliographical sources. It is probably that many of the students did not achieve public recognition, but users of the collection who can further identify them are urged to consult with the Department's Manuscript Librarian.
  - School of Illustration, Chicago: student and staff work, (40 items). (Box 16)
  - School of Illustration, Chicago: student and staff work, (48 items). (Box 17)
  - School of Illustration, Chicago: student and staff work, (53 items). (Box 18)
  - Oil paintings by Cyrus LeRoy Baldridge (2 items), Post-Holme era. (Box 19)
- Series V: Biographical Material, 1898-1945?
  - Biographical material. 1898-1945? (Box 20)
    Dean Eva. F. H. Ysleta, Texas: Edwin B. Hill, 1935
    Frank Holme Memorial Group. Bulletin. no. 1-21, 1938-1945?
    Gjelsness, Rudolph H. Frank Holme: Newspaper Artist and Designer of Books. New York, 1935. Extract from The Colophone, n.s., no. 2
    Goudy, Frederic W. Frank Holme. Ysleta, Texas, 1942. "these notes... are transcripts from conversations with Fred W. Goudy by one of the students in the School of Illustrations."
    Hammond, John C. Founder of the Bandar Log Club and his Meteoric Career. Ysleta, Texas: Edwin B. Hill, 1936
    Hill, Edwin B. Frank Holme: A Friend. Ysleta, Texas: Edwin B. Hill, 1904
    Hill, Edwin B. More Than a Memory. Ysleta, Texas: Edwin B. Hill, 1936 (2 copies)
    McDougall, Isabel. "Frank Holme, Newspaper Artist." Chicago, 1898. Extracted from Brush and Pencil, v. 2, 1898 (photocopy)
- Series VI: Bandar Log Press Books, 1895-1903
  - Holme, Frank. Just For Fun; a collection of humorous verses from various pens. Chicago, Ill. December 1895 (Box 21)
    Number 19 of 74 copies.
  - Dryden, Charles. Swanson, Able Seaman; the melancholy fate of a hapless mariner. Pictures by Frank Holme. Ashville, North Carolina. December 1901 (Box 21)
    Number 124 of 174 copies, cover was put on up-side-down.
  - LaShelle, Kirke. Where is Ray Brown? Asheville, North Carolina. April 1902 (Box 21)
    Number 27 of 174 copies, embellished by Frank Holme.
  - LaShelle, Kirke. Poker Rubaiyat; Phoenix, Arizona. January 1903 (Box 21)
    Number 113 of 274, illustrations by Frank Holme.
  - Holme, Frank. All About the Bandar Log Press; Phoenix, Arizona. October 1903 (Box 21)
  - Ade, George. The Strenuous Lad's Library. No. 1-3, Phoenix, Arizona. 1903 (Box 21)
    No. 1 "Handsome Cyril," or "The Messenger Boy with Warm Feet." (2 copies)
    No. 2 "Clarence Allen," or "The Hypnotic Boy Journalist." (2 copies)
    No. 3 "Rollo Johnson," or "The Demon Bicycle and Its Daring Rider." (2 copies)
  - Robinson, William H. Her Navajo Lover. Phoenix, Arizona. 1903 (Box 21)
    Woodcuts by Frank Holme, (4 copies)